Charles Jones

cbj3@chuckbjones.com www.chuckbjones.com 281-814-7223

Background

I am a jack-of-all-trades programmer with over **20 years** experience, currently spending most of my time on **backend web** development. I've done my fair share of **mobile** app development and general **client/server** development as well. I am passionate about **open-source** software and writing software that people love using.

Skills

- Web: Ruby/Rails, Java, HTML5, CSS, Javascript/ECMAScript, MySQL, MongoDB, CouchDB, RESTful HTTP APIs
- Mobile: Android Java, Apple iOS Objective C
- Unix/Linux system development: C/C++, Ruby, Go, Python, Perl, Shell (Bash) scripting, Containers (Docker)
- Learning: Rust, Microservice architectures, Cloud infrastructure (AWS), GraphQL

Experience

Elastic Suite - Emerald Expositions, LLC

Sr. Manager Backend Development – 2021 to 2023

- Led multiple, dispersed teams of backend **Ruby on Rails** developers developing both core application features and custom client enhancements and integrations.
- Worked closely with Product Owner and UX team to refine requirements and architect solutions for new features.
- Migrated local database-backed authentication scheme to AWS Cognito for all 200+ Elastic Suite sites, allowing for federated identity sharing among new applications and with other partners.

Elastic Suite - PlumRiver, LLC

Senior Software Developer - 2016 to 2021

- Led small backend development team of an enterprise Ruby on Rails application with MongoDB, Postgres, ElasticSearch, Redis, S3, and Memcached.
- Worked directly with clients to design and develop custom integrations, such as real-time inventory update **APIs**.
- Scaled the whitelabel **B2B e-commerce** application from 17 to more than 200 sites by developing configuration-driven **ETL** process and automating **CI/CD**.

Educational Technology Center - Texas State University, San Marcos, TX

Senior Programmer Analyst – 2014 to 2016

- Led development of the university's Android and iOS applications.
- Developed policy and guidelines mandating mobile-friendly web design for all university websites.
- Implemented caching proxy server in **Go** for distributed microservices that enabled efficient access of these services by many different applications and thousands of users.

Programmer Analyst II – 2009 to 2014

- Modified and maintained open-source Java-based CMS that hosts 300+ university websites.
 Developed custom site templates, created new features, fixed bugs (and submitted them back upstream), and integrated the application with other university systems.
- Developed several **Ruby on Rails** applications including a workshop reservation system and the University Events Calendar, both used by dozens of departments across the university.
- Maintained a web-crawler that scans university websites for dead links using Lifecycle and the open-source **Python** Linkchecker software, and submitted several bug-fixes upstream.

Systems Application Engineering, Inc. - Houston, TX

Systems Analyst – 2002 to 2009

- Created **mobile** applications on **DOS** and **Windows-CE** based mobile devices for food distribution and other industries.
- Wrote the server-side applications they communicated with, running on Windows or Unix platforms.

- Implemented **RESTful API** to legacy server application by writing **CGI** scripts in **ANSI C** generating **XML** responses to queries on the application's data.
- Designed, implemented, and maintained an application framework in C# for writing extensible mobile applications on Windows CE. Wrote modules for wireless TCP/IP communications, Bluetooth printing, Bar Code scanning, and i18n.
- Implemented client/server system for alcohol/tobacco tax collection at ports of entry along Texas/Mexico border. Wrote a single client application in C# that cross-compiled to both Windows Mobile and desktop Windows platforms.
- Wrote warehouse logistics client/server system that utilized Text-To-Speech, Voice Recognition and Bar Code Scanning to direct users and record their input.
- Created custom **HTTP** client in **C++** and custom **XML**-based template language to facilitate implementation of **voice** enabled applications on mobile devices.

Education

M.S. Computer Science, 2013

Texas State University, San Marcos, TX

B.S. Computer Engineering, 2001

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA